Finding Aid for Ana Luisa Cardona papers, 1973-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ana Luisa Cardona papers 1973-2011
Cardona, Ana Luisa.
510 MB online
1 oversize folder
3 linear feet
2010015 Aa 2; UAm
Member of Casa de Unidad and the Alliance for Cultural Democracy. Collection contains grant materials for Casa de Unidad, material related to other Michigan Latino arts organizations as well as Michigan Latino artists. Also photographs, interviews, and other material related to photographers Jack Delano and Julio Perazza.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came from Ana Luisa Cardona (donor no. 10213 ) in June 2009 and April 2014.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Ana Luisa Cardona served as administrator of Latino arts and cultural programs, was an executive director of the Casa de Unidad Cultural Arts and Media Center in Detroit, the Raza Art & Media Collective (RAMC), Nuestras Artes de Michigan. Cardona is the founding board member of Artes Unidas de Michigan, a statewide partnership of organizations working to advance Latino arts and artists in Michigan. She served in an advisory role to VSA arts of Michigan and the Rural Arts and Culture Initiative of the Michigan Council for the Arts and Cultural Affairs. She was also involved in the Alliance for Cultural Democracy, where she was a participant at the 9th Annual Conference and served as a contact for some of their bulletins. Cardona also has served on the National Endowment for the Humanities national review panel; was an Arts Management Fellow for the National Endowments for the Arts; served as a Consultant for Arts Education for Michigan Department of Education; and was member of the Michigan Department of Education's King*Chavez*Parks Initiative. She also held a Research Associate appointment with Michigan State University Museum.
Artist, columnist, photographer, and poet, she lectured and written for various publications and periodicals. Cardona interviewed Jack Delano, a photographer for the Farm Security Administration. Delano came to the University of Michigan as a visiting artist in 1984.
Cardona holds Masters of Arts degrees in Instructional Design and Technology, and in History of Art with a specialization in Museum Practice from the University of Michigan.
The papers of Ana Luisa Cardona document her activities in Casa de Unidad and the Alliance for Cultural Democracy, as well as her association with Jack Delano. This collection contains the following series: Casa de Unidad, Jack Delano, Julio Perazza, and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Alliance for Cultural Democracy.; Casa de Unidad (Detroit, Mich.); Cardona, Ana Luisa.; Delano, Jack.; Perazza, Julio.; Hispanic Americans--Michigan--Detroit.
Genre Terms:
Oral histories.; Videotapes.
- Casa de Unidad 1983-1994
  The Casa de Unidad series contains materials for grants that Cardona was involved in, correspondence and basic materials related to the organization such as bylaws and financial information.
  - Arts Agenda 1991 (Box 1)
  - Audit report 1989 (Box 1)
  - Board minutes 1989 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Calendario del Barrio 1985 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1989-1990, 1994 (Box 1)
  - El Barrio Southwest Detroit Directory 1985 (Box 1)
  - Festival 1990 (Box 1)
  - Finances 1987-1991 (Box 1)
  - Financial reports 1989 (Box 1)
  - Flyers 1985-1986, circa 1991 (Box 1)
  - Grant application 1983-1987 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Grant application for Expansion Arts 1984 (Box 1)
  - Grant application for Michigan Council for the Arts, Michigan Council for the Humanities and Expansion Arts 1987-1992 (Box 1)
  - Group photograph undated (Box 1)
  - Handwritten notes undated (Box 1)
  - Initiatives 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Letters to the Michigan Council for the Arts in response to discontinuation of funding 1984, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1985-1992 (scattered), undated (Box 1)
  - Notas de El Barrio 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets and postcards 1988-1989, circa 2001 (Box 1)
  - "Report on City of Detroit Community Development Block Grant from July 1986 to June 1988" 1989 (Box 1)
  - Reports to the Board 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - Strategic Plan, 1988/1989-1990/1991 (draft) 1988 (Box 1)
  - Unity in the Community September 6, 1984, VHS tape (Box 1)
- Jack Delano 1973-2004
  Jack Delano was a photographer for the Farm Security Administration and a composer influenced by Puerto Rican folk material. He moved to Puerto Rico in 1946. This series contains an interview with Jack Delano conducted by Ana Cardona, materials concerning Jack Delano's performance at Hostos Community College and his role as a visiting artist to the University of Michigan, his correspondence with Cardona (1985 and 1987), notes, photographs and video recordings by and about Delano.
  - Videotapes of talks and photography exhibitions (identification uncertain)
    - Jack delano's art, Beta L500 (Box 1)
    - Jack Delano's film "Night", Beta L500 (Box 1)
    - Jack Delano's last day speaking by Julio Perazza, Beta L500 (Box 1)
    - Jack Delano speaking first day, Beta L500 (Box 1)
    - Jack talk at 12:00 noon Art School, Beta L500 (Box 1)
    - Jack slides, Beta L500 (Box 1)
    - Jack Delano, third talk, Beta L500 (Box 1)
    - Jack at Aup. Art School, Beta L500 (Box 1)
    - Unidentified title, Beta L500 (Box 1)
    - Interviews probably given by Cardona. Topics include Detroit and Casa de Unidad, VHS (Box 1)
  - Cardona paper about Delano (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Cardona 1985, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Handwritten notes undated (Box 1)
  - Hostos Community College, Delano and Bronx Arts Ensembles Orchestra program 1983
    - Article, performance program, flyer (Box 1)
    - "Delano performance", audio cassette (Box 1)
    - Negatives and photographic proof pages (Box 1)
  - Interview with Delano conducted by Ana Cardona 1983 (Box 2)
    - Transcription (Box 2)
    - Audio cassette tape (Box 2)
    - Interview in digital format, .ZIP file
  - "Mass Communication and Hispanic Americans", literature review and bibliography 1980 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1982, circa 1989 (Box 2)
  - Photographic proof which contains an image of Delano (Box 2)
  - Photographs undated, 1941-1942, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Visiting Artist to University of Michigan 1984 (Box 2)
- Julio Perazza 1970s-2001
  Julio Perazza was a Detroit, Mich. Latino photographer and teacher. He was born in San Juan, Puerto Rico in 1943. After graduating from Western High School in Detroit, Perazza studied at various places, including Highland Park Community College. He eventually completed his B.F.A. in photography at the University of Michigan (1975) and his M.F.A. in photography from Eastern Michigan University. Perazza toured as a performer and photographer with the musical performing arts company "Up with People". The subjects of his photographs were African-Americans in Detroit, Chicanos in Michigan, and life in his homeland of Puerto Rico. His artwork has been exhibited throughout Michigan and around the United States.
  The Perazza series includes video recordings made by Perazza in cooperation with other Michigan artists, photographs by Perazza, a photo album with photographs of Perazza exhibit that was curated by Ana Cardona, and biographical material.
  - Los Viejitos, 1 UCA 30 videotape and 1 VHS videotape (Box 2)
  - Photographs, approximately from circa 1978-1985 (Box 2)
  - "Photography of Julio Perazza" (Box 2)
    (photo album)
  - Remembering Photographer Julio Perazza 2001 (Box 2)
    (includes color photograph)
  - Video recordings, 5 videotapes VHS [TM] (Box 2)
- Topical Files 1978-2000
  The Topical Files contain documentation of Cardona's involvement in the Alliance for Cultural Democracy, Cardona's writings and biographical information, administrative records and calendars of Artes Unidas de Michigan. The Raza Art and Media Collective (RAMC) folder includes negatives of portraits and publications. Of special interest are video interviews of Detroit los Repatriados, Mexicans who were deported from the U.S. in the 1930s, taken by Nora Mendoza in 2004. Also sound recordings of interviews and monologs on various subjects, in Spanish and English, as well as Latin music.
  - Alliance for Cultural Democracy 1985-1989 (scattered), undated (Box 2)
  - Alliance for Cultural Democracy 1986-1989, undated (Box 2)
  - Ana Cardona's biographical information (Box 2)
  - Ana Cardona's writings (Box 2)
  - Artes Unidas de Michigan 2001-2007
    - Board and Circle of Advisors Meeting 2003 (Box 2)
    - Calendario 2006 (Box 2)
    - Calendario (related material) 2005, .ZIP file
    - Directory of organizations 2004, .ZIP file
    - Various (Box 2)
    - Web page (Box 2)
  - Conferences
    - Latina/o Workers Leadership Institute (University of Michigan) 2007 (Box 3)
    - Preparing Our Students for the World (Michigan State University) 2007 (Box 3)
  - Detroit Latino Agenda for the 1990s (Box 3)
  - Latin Eyes: Spain 2011 by Ana Luisa Cardona and Daniel del Solar (Box 3)
  - Latino arts flyers, catalogues, etc. 1984-2007 scattered (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1978, 1987-1988, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, poetry, and 'An Adult's Lesson in Civics' essay 1997, .ZIP file
  - National Endowment for the Arts Hispanic Task Force on Latino Arts 1977 (Box 3)
    (includes photographs)
  - Nora Mendoza Los Repatriados interviews (Box 3)
    - Interviews. 2003-2004, miniDV tapes (Box 3)
      - Airport June 12, 2004 (Box 3)
      - Café Cubano circa 2004 (Box 3)
      - "Coming Back," circa 2004 (Box 3)
      - June 2004 Conference, 10 videotapes Mini-DV (Box 3)
      - Mexican Consul May 7, 2004, 2 videotapes Mini-DV (Box 3)
      - Mujeres circa 2004 (Box 3)
      - September 20, 2003, 2 videotapes Mini-DV (Box 3)
    - 2005, VHS video tape (Box 3)
  - Pá Lante lecture/demo at eastern Michigan University March 26, 1985, Beta L-750 video cassette (Box 3)
  - Raza Art and Media Collective (RAMC) (Box 3)
  - Sound recordings undated, 1980, 1982, 25 audio cassettes (Box 3)
  - Southmost Story 1996, .ZIP file
    (budgets, strategic plan, to do lists, e-mail, etc.; includes numerous documents related to Western International High School)
  - America the Beautiful poster (Folder UAm)
  - Anti-war and political posters in Spanish (Folder UAm)
    (one poster is dated 1968)
  - "Fall into the Arts" Downtown Battle Creek Annual Art Walk 2011 (Folder UAm)
    (mounted poster and Cardona's biography)
  - Southwest Detroit's Clark Park posters (printed by Casa de Unidad printshop) and for the 9th Annual Conference of the Alliance for Cultural Democracy circa 1985 (Folder UAm)
Related Materials
The Bentley Historical Library holds the following related manuscript materials:
Casa de Unidad (Detroit, Mich.) records, 1980-2006.
Julio Perazza visual materials collection, 1973-2004 (scattered dates).
Printed materials published by Casa de Unidad held by the Bentley Library include:
El Barrio, 1982-1992 .Call number: EA 115 C334 B253
El Barrio Southwest Detroit Directory, 1984-1985. Call number: EA 115 C334 B253d
Notas del Barrio, 1985, 1988-1989, 1995, 1997/1998. Call number: EA 115 C334 N899